Finding Aid for Letty M. Wickliffe papers, ca. 1860s-ca. 1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Letty M. Wickliffe papers ca. 1860s-ca. 1992 1960s-1976
Wickliffe, Letty M., 1902-
0.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
9745 Aa 2
Teacher; Ann Arbor, Michigan, community activist; member of the North Central Property Owners Association in Ann Arbor. Articles written for the local newspaper, awards, scattered correspondence, biographical information, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Letty M. Wickliffe (Donor No. 8190 ) in October, 1993.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born on January 25, 1902, in Ann Arbor, Michigan, Letty Wickliffe is the daughter of an escaped slave, Joseph Holt Wickliffe and Mary Jewett Wickliffe. She grew up in the Ann Arbor area and attended the University of Michigan, receiving a bachelor's degree in education in 1924 and a master's degree in psychology in 1938.
Letty Wickliffe taught from 1924 to 1928 in a segregated Dallas, Texas, high school before moving to Indianapolis, Indiana where she spent the remainder of her educational career at Crispus Attucks High School, a school serving the African-American community. While there she was head of the Department of Exceptional Children for forty years and received various awards for her work in the field of education. Former student, now actor Meshach Taylor, was so influenced by Wickliffe that he invited her to appear on the television talk show "Vicki!" as the teacher who made the most difference in his life.
After retiring in 1969, she returned to her hometown of Ann Arbor to begin a second career as a community activist and volunteer for the Republican party. Among the organizations that she headed or played an integral role in are the North Central Property Owner's Association, Ann Arbor 2000 Board, Ann Arbor Public Library Advisory Committee, Kerrytown Council Board, and the Citizen's Association for Area Planning. She also served the Republican party as vice chair of the Washtenaw County Committee, a member of the Republican City Committee, and a candidate for several local offices. In addition, she was an alternate delegate at the 1980 convention and attended the Reagan/Bush inaugural ceremonies in 1981.
Letty Wickliffe has received many awards and honors for her participation in her many endeavors. These awards include a Citation for Distinguished Professional Leadership by the Council for Exceptional Children, a listing in Who's Who in Special Education, the Book of Golden Deeds Award and a Presidential Certificate of Appreciation from George Bush. More recently, she was honored by a 90th birthday party celebration, which was attended by the many friends she has made throughout her educational and retirement careers.
The Letty M. Wickliffe collection documents the life of a devoted educator, Ann Arbor community activist, and active member of the Republican party. The collection is divided into two series, Topical and Visual. Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series and the items inside the folders are in chronological order.
Subjects:
Wickliffe, Letty M., 1902-; Civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African American women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Wickliffe, Letty M., 1902-; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor--ca. 1915.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; North Central Property Owners Association.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; University of Michigan. School of Education. Class of 1924.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical File
  The Topical series contains material concerning awards and relating news clippings dating from 1976 to approximately 1992, diplomas and certificates from 1924 to 1961, letters of recognition spanning from 1980 to 1988, news clippings concerning her family dating from 1938 to 1968, and a copy of her resume. There is also a folder of correspondence that contains one letter to the trustees of the Ann Arbor School Board dated 1980 and a folder of newspaper letters to the editor and a guest editorial.
  - Awards, 1976-ca. 1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Education (diploma, certificates), 1924-1961 (Box 1)
  - Family, 1938-ca. 1968 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Recognition, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles (letters to the editor, guest editorial), 1981-ca. 1992 (Box 1)
  - Resume, ca. 1993 (Box 1)
- Visual Material
  The Visual series is divided into two subseries of photographs and slides. The five folders and one oversize box of photographs deal primarily with Wickliffe's class pictures, family and friends. The oversize box contains a photo album of black and white photographs and an album documenting Wickliffe's 90th birthday celebration. Also included are photographs of Wickliffe with various Republican officials including one photograph with George Bush which was taken in 1987. Of possible interest to researchers are three candid and distant photographs of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. on the steps of a church in Montgomery, Alabama in the 1960s.
  The slides subseries contains seven folders of slides taken for various North Central Property Owners Association projects. Included are folders dealing with aerial views of Ann Arbor, the interiors of neighborhood homes, maps, planning charts and reports, site analyses of a child care center and park plans and many slides of neighborhood streets and houses. Slides in this subseries are dated from approximately 1968 to 1976 with the bulk of them being from the 1974 time period. Anyone interested in studying the development of Ann Arbor's North Central area in this time span would find these slides useful.
  - Photographs
    - Class Pictures, ca. 1913-ca. 1970 (Box 1)
    - Family, 1860s-ca. 1925, See also family album in oversized Box 2 (Box 1)
    - Letty Wickliffe Portraits and Informal Photos, ca. 1915-ca. 1985 (Box 1)
    - King, Martin Luther (Montgomery, Alabama), ca. 1960s (Box 1)
    - Ninetieth Birthday Celebration, 1992 (Box 1)
      (see framed portrait and album of memorabilia in oversized Box 2)
  - Slides--North Central Property Owners Association
    - Aerial Views, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Interiors of Homes, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Maps and Charts, ca. 1972 (Box 1)
    - Neighborhood Views, ca. 1968-ca. 1976 (Box 1)
    - Parks, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Reports and Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Site Analyses, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Framed portrait and album of memorabilia (Box 2)